The world of the vibe coder is going to
find this very frustrating because it's
going to slow them down. And the idea of
having gone from seeing outputs in 20
minutes to an hour to seeing outputs at
the end of a 6-hour documentation
session will be inherently frustrating.
A repository with linted code that had
2, three, 400 unit tests, automation
tests, an architecturally separate front
end and back end infrastructure as code.
And I think that any startup that isn't
leveraging this build methodology is
going to find it very hard to compete.
You know, the vast majority of, for
example, Y Combinator startups are using
AI tooling to to to build much if not
all of their code. um a statistic I
don't want to misquote but some you know
incredibly high percentage of of
startups in white combinator using tools
like this um it just gives that sort of
competitive edge and the world of of
building product just looks so different
now be because anybody can show up with
a vibe coded prototype and and show
something shiny to investors but
actually transitioning it into something
that would scale to the first even 500
or a thousand users is a very different
question um and I I feel like spec
driven is like the the methodology for
doing this.
>> Yeah. And I think it's it's it's
interesting. I see when I see spec
driven approaches and I see kind of more
prompt driven approaches, you almost
like start looking at a prompt driven
approach being a very prototype style
way of doing things. I've even known
someone to start with a prompt driven uh
approach. Then they send their kind of
like claude logs or whatever it is over
and say, "Look, build me a a spec based
on these prompts. you know, from my
prompts where my intents are. You can
see from the code that's been generated,
what has been built, what I'm happy
with. Uh, build a spec that represents
this. And I and I and I guess kind of
like do you feel like that if you were
to like go fully vibe in like prompts uh
without without building a spec? Does do
do you feel like that would be like a
strong limiter for people who actually
want to go much further, much closer to
production, those who want to scale AI
within their organizations? As you've
probably gathered, like that's kind of
the framework of how I think of things
that have purely been prompted. Like
that's not to say that you couldn't
construct a perfect prompt that actually
encapsulates all of the context from
your specs and just perfectly right
sizes your context window such that it's
built, you know, task by task, a bunch
of different um a bunch of different
smaller stories in just, you know, very
wellcraftrafted prompts. That's
definitely possible. But the methodology
of spec driven with the combination of a
framework makes you more likely to be
successful. Yeah. Um what's also
interesting is like you know is spec
driven what the future of AI native
engineering looks like. Like I'm not
actually that dogged on the fact that it
is. I'm not completely convinced. Um it
feels as though cursor in particular has
been slow to adopt a lot of the
primitives and instead gone through the
[clears throat] the their recent release
with plan mode feels like a a a spec
similar to spec driven or spec driven
compatible way of operation but it's not
exactly that. Um so like you know it
feels like the best approximation right
now of how to work with these models
this this this spec driven methodology
and also the BMAT framework itself. But
that's not to say that you know next
year that's that that's what things are
going to look like. My uh if I've
learned one thing in the world of the in
the kind of whirlwind that's been the
last nine months um it is that my
crystal ball is inherently faulty and I
will make terrible [laughter]
>> who knows.
>> Yeah. Uh the crystal ball will be I I
saw an eightball uh the other day where
it's an LLM. It's an LLM implemented
eightball which is like oh yeah every
everything's everything's going in the
future. So the crystal
>> by any chance repeatedly say you're
>> you're absolutely right. [laughter]
So so when we when we think about how
LLMs you know typically are are kind of
like better with the the more structured
specs uh with with kind of like clear
requirements. When we think about those
specifications or those systems that are
poorly specified, what do they become?
Do they become something which just you
know holds technical debt or are they
now a liability uh because because of
the way an LLM is going to is
essentially going to implement that and
and and make assumptions.
>> Yeah, it's an interesting kind of
question, isn't it? Like what be becomes
of technical debt? Does you know do we
have this new thing that is spec debt or
requirements debt or you know inadequate
requirements? Because when you think
about a tech debt, surely should at
least fade into the background. Um
because it's now easier to tackle
backlogs of tech debt through agentic
coding, right? You know, the sort of
drudgery of well actually it doesn't
feel like drudgery. Sometimes it's
really rewarding, but but the the art of
like eliminating tech debt is now much
easier to to go after with an agentic
coding system typically. So you know
does that become really important um
when you can solve for tech debt much
easier and in fact it's actually
something that's not really aligned to
what you wanted to build that becomes
you know the problem. So like poorly
defined requirements um does it become
harder after going through you know
three four days worth of of spec driven
development where you suddenly have this
20 30,000 line repository is it actually
harder to recover from the fact that you
missed some requirements along the way
and is there flexibility sufficient in
the workflow to be able to make up for
that
>> um certainly some of the techniques I've
tried have been things like injecting
new backlog items to the end of a a
backlog to try and recover and still
following the spec driven methodology
rather than sort of bailing to vibe
coding which is definitely a temptation
but following the the methodology to
sort of steer towards the the desired
output. Um but yeah, it's it's
definitely tricky.